What would the beekeepers eat?
那养蜂的人又吃什么呢
This is an age-old inequality.
这就是一个亘古不变的不等式
Is the bee colony living for the beekeepers?
到底蜂群是为了养蜂人而活啊
Are beekeepers really keeping bees or harming them?
养蜂人到底是养蜂人还是害蜂的人啊
This is an age-old paradox.
这就是一个亘古不变的悖论啊
I always take out the trash whenever I go out.
我呢我每次出门扔垃圾
The type of person I hate the most is someone who asks me if they should throw away their trash.
我最烦的一种人就是从我手里边儿问我
Because when I watch short videos, they tell me,
垃圾要不要扔的人啊
if I give them my trash,
因为我刷短视频上面告诉我
and they use it or eat something from it,
如果我把垃圾给了他
and then get sick,
那么他用这个垃圾或者吃了垃圾里的东西
they might sue me.
生了病
I thought, 'How can someone be so nasty?'
他就要告我
So every time, I make sure to walk carefully to the garbage station.
我心想卧槽人怎么可以这么坏
So, I always make a point to walk to the waste station carefully.
所以我每次都会认认真真的走到垃圾站
Throw the trash down
把垃圾扔下
Then wait for them to pick it up
然后等他们再去捡
Absolutely avoid any conversation with them
绝对不跟他们发生对话啊
Later, I observed these people carefully I found them so peculiar Why did their accents sound so different from mine? Then I realized Many people's lives are completely different from mine
后来我仔细观察这些人 我觉得这些人怎么这么的奇怪啊 为什么这些人的口音都跟我不一样啊 后来我就发现 其实很多人的人生完完全全跟我不一样啊
When I was bored
在我闲的无聊
run to the nearby Small Park
跑到这个周围的小公园
to watch the seniors exercise
去看大爷大妈健身的时候
that's when I noticed
我这时候就在发现
even though they're all seniors
其实同样是大爷大妈
there are two completely different outcomes
却有完全不同的两种结局啊
some seniors, like my parents
有些大爷大妈就比如我父母
and all my relatives
还有我的所有这些亲戚一样啊
worked at various organizations when they were young
他们年轻的时候在各个单位工作
and now they have a stable pension
老了时候呢就有稳定的退休金
So when we get old,
所以呢老了以后呢
we could either join others in square dancing,
要么就是像一些人似的去跳广场舞啊
or ballroom dancing,
跳交际舞啊
go out for photography,
出去摄影啊
walk our birds,
遛鸟啊
go fishing,
钓鱼啊
or we could be like my parents,
要么就像我爸妈这样
watching short dramas at home,
在家看看短剧啊
or listening to storytelling.
听听评书啊
Life is quite laid-back.
生活过得很悠闲
But there are other elderly folks.
但是有另一种老头老太太呢
You'll find the old men doing odd jobs.
你会发他们老头呢在打零工
Temporary work, you know.
打短工啊
In their seventies or so.
几十岁的年纪了啊
Still working on road repairs.
仍然在修路啊
Still digging holes. Still picking up trash. And the old ladies, they're not just cleaning toilets. They are picking up all sorts of discarded bottles and such. Or they might be looking after children for others. Or they could be doing all kinds of domestic work.
仍然在挖洞 仍然在捡垃圾 老太太呢不是在扫厕所啊 就是在捡各种各样的废品瓶子之类的 要不就是替人带孩子 要不就是在做各种各样保姆式的工作
You'll find that these aunts and uncles,
你会发现这些大姐这些大爷们啊
these grandmas, you can actually encounter them in various malls.
这些老太太其实你在各个商场的时候都能遇到
You’re bound to run into them when you use the restroom.
你上厕所的时候肯定会遇到他们啊
Sometimes it’s an old man,
有的时候是大爷
and sometimes it’s an old woman in the restroom.
有的时候是大妈在这个厕所
And then there’s the subway station.
在这个啊地铁站啊
These spots for transportation
交通的这些地方啊
like the library and concert hall
图书馆音乐厅啊
you're likely to encounter someone taking a single ride
上场你都能碰上这种带一单吧
So, we're back to the initial question
啊那么又回到了最开始的一个问题
Is the beekeeper's goal to produce honey for consumption
到底养蜂人养蜂目的是为了吃蜂蜜
or to raise bees?
还是为了养蜜蜂呢
Why are they called beekeepers?
为什么要叫它养蜂人呢
Who ultimately gets the honey produced by the bees?
那蜂蜜产生的蜜蜂产生的蜂蜜最终归了谁呢
You need to think carefully about this question
自己要仔细想想这个问题
Actually, if you look at these elderly men and women, many of them
其实你看这些大爷大妈很多的人来讲
they enjoy, well, how can I put it,
他们享受的是怎么说呢
they basically don't have any pension.
是基本上没有什么退休金的啊
Farmers have it very tough,
农民就是这样非常的苦
so when they get old,
所以他到老了以后
they have no choice but to continue working,
他不得已他要继续工作
they have to keep working, to support their entire family. Of course, every rural area is different. There are wealthy and poor areas in the countryside but for most people they still need to work they still need to use this method of working
他要继续工作 才能养活一家老小啊 当然来讲每一个地方的农村不一样 农村有富的有穷的 但是大部分人来讲 仍然需要去工作 仍然需要用这工作的方法
either by begging
要么乞讨
or working
要么工作
or by various means to support their families
要么以各种方式来养家糊口
selling some goods
卖一些东西
so this is the significant difference between rural and urban areas
所以来讲这就是城乡之间的巨大差别
The significant differences brought by different identities
身份之间带来的巨大差别
When you think about it every day
当你每天去想啊
I want to drive a Lamborghini
我要开兰博基尼啊
I want to live in a spacious apartment
我要住大平层
When I want to buy a house in Vancouver
我要去温哥华买房的时候
Don't forget about many of your fellow countrymen
你要不要忘了你的很多同胞
Who are still in such a survival situation
仍然是这么一种生存的状况
Your parents
你的父母啊
For the majority of our audience's parents
大多数我们的观众的父母来讲
Actually, it's pretty similar to my parents.
其实跟我的父母差不多啊
When it comes to daily life,
都是生活来讲的话
it's relatively stable,
比较起码说稳定啊
not exactly luxurious,
不能说多么优渥
but stable at least.
起码是稳定
But this person is afraid of comparisons,
但这个人就是怕相比一比起啊
when you compare,
一比较之下
you realize,
其实你会发现
society never really lives up to our so-called ideals.
这个社会呢永远谈不上我们所谓的
Absolute fairness
绝对的公平啊
Continuous development
永远发展
This phase is relative
这是阶段是相对的
When I was young, I had the opportunity to study in North America It was actually a chance encounter But the home front remains our honest truth A commonly used phrase They sold everything to send me to school It was indeed very tough
是我年轻的时候呢有幸呢去北美读了书啊 这其实是一次偶然的机会 但是家里的哈仍然是咱们说实话啊 常用的一句词 砸锅卖铁送我去读书 确实是非常不容易
But it opened my eyes to a whole new world.
但是却让我人生开了一个眼界
You'll notice,
你会发现啊
in areas with a high concentration of Chinese people,
在华人比较多的牛
like New York and Los Angeles,
纽约洛杉矶呀
Vancouver,
温哥华
Toronto, and places like that,
多伦多这种地方的话
you'll see the majority of
你会见到大部分啊
all the social strata from Chinese society,
中国社会的所个所谓的所有的阶层的人
from the lower-income individuals
从底层的这些人
They started working after they came out
他们出来以后打工
and then rose to the middle class
然后翻身到中层
These people continued working in middle-class jobs after they came out
这些人出来以后出来以后继续干中层的工工作
and felt their social status rise to the upper class
然后感觉到阶级下降到顶层
These wealthy individuals came out
这些富豪出来啊
buying things
买东买西
buying apartments and houses
买楼买房啊
spending extravagantly
大肆挥霍
you would find it's completely different
你会发现完完全全是不一样的
When living in the country
人生在国内的时候
Generally speaking
基本上来讲
Due to the large population
因为人口基数大
Because of the numerous cities
因为城市分布多
Due to the segregation of social circles
因为社交圈层的相互隔离
You don’t run into these people
你碰不到这些人
But when it comes to living abroad
但是在国外来讲
I mentioned
我说了
In a city like Vancouver
在温哥华这样的城市来讲
There's a high concentration of Chinese people.
华人比较集中啊
So you'll always encounter people from different social strata.
所以你总会碰到不同阶层的
Wealthy individuals from various regions. This can shape your values. It can have a significant impact on your worldview. All the wealthy people tend to gather in one city. What happens then?
不同地方的有钱人啊 所以就会对你的价值观形成的 会产生非常大的冲击啊 所有的有钱人都会集中在一个城市里边儿 这时候会发生什么
This is when class conflicts become evident.
这时候就是阶级矛盾的一个具体的一个体现
Of course, there are also cultural clashes in the area.
当然在当地又有文化冲突
There are racial conflicts
又有种族矛盾
There are class conflicts
又有阶级矛盾
At such times, things get really interesting
在这个时候就会非常有意思
So it helps me understand
所以就会让我明白了
Actually, transcending class mentality is quite common
其实跨越阶级的思维是很正常的
Throughout my life
所以在我的一生当中
If you talk about absolute fairness
如果你说追求绝对的公平
Absolute justice
绝对的正义
Then let me tell you
那我跟你说
Doing this is absolutely futile.
这样做绝对是徒劳的
Because most people don't want to change the status quo.
因为大部分人并不会想啊利益出去改变现状
And absolute fairness will never truly exist.
而且绝对的公平也不会绝对的出现
There's something you need to understand.
一一让你要知道一件事
The people you think are exploiting others now,
就是现在的你所谓的啊那个剥削人的人
were actually in a state of being exploited in the past.
实际上以前就是一个被剥削的状态
Many things are just a matter of perspective.
很多东西就是关系掉个个儿啊
The previously oppressed individuals are now in power.
新的这个以前被压迫的人上了
Once they rise to power,
上来了以后呢
He continues to exploit
他又剥削啊
Carry on with new people
继续新的人
So in many cases
所以很多的时候来讲
In a capitalist society
在资本社会当中
These relations of production won't change
这种生产关系是不会改变的
But what can we do in our limited lives? For example, we can do things like Pangdolai Provide more equitable job opportunities for society There's also something I often mention You can establish a foundation.
但是我们在我们有限的人生当中能做些什么呢 比如我们能做胖东来那样的事情啊 为这社会提供更多的公平的工作机会 还有一种就像我经常说的 你可以成立基金会
With 2 million, 4 million, or 8 million to set up a foundation.
200万400万800万设立基金会啊
Save a lot of money.
存很多的钱
And then provide dedicated assistance to these people through the foundation.
然后去为这些人专门的提供基金上面那帮助你
As a person,
作为一个人
just like environmental protection,
就像环境保护一样
in many cases,
其实很多的时候来讲
we don't need to talk about the greenhouse effect anymore,
温室效应咱们已经不用再说了
from 2019 to now.
2019年到现在
Every day is marked by extreme heat.
每天都是极端的炎热天气啊
Actually, humans once had a chance to restore the Earth's ecosystem.
其实人类本来是有机会去啊恢复地球的生态的
But we missed that opportunity forever.
但是却永远错过了这个机会
So, in reality,
所以在现实当中
as a human being,
你作为一个人
let alone being a young life,
作为一个更不用说你是一个年轻的生命
what you can do,
你能够做到的事情
just surviving is already a significant challenge.
在光是你的生存来讲就已经是很不容易了
So, in our lives,
所以在我们这个生命当中
In our finite lives,
有限的生命当中
we need to understand,
我们要明白
you will have to coexist with all sorts of things you disapprove of,
你要长期的与各种各样的你看不惯的事情
negative phenomena,
不良的现象
or what you believe should not exist in an ideal society, in the books you read, in your school, in the education system, things you cannot see. But still, as I mentioned at the beginning There are so many people like this
或者说你觉得在理想的社会当中 在你的书本当中 在你的学校 教育系统中 你看不见的东西 但是还是像最开始我说的那句话 很多的很多的这样的人
At first, you see them as part of the intelligentsia
你刚一开始你对他们作为一个知识分子啊
As a child of the middle class
作为一个中产阶级的孩子
Don't deny that you're middle class
你不要不承认自己是中产阶级
If you weren't middle class
你如果你不是中产阶级
You wouldn't be watching Bilibili
你不会看B站
You'd be using other apps
你会刷其他的软件
You wouldn't have this setup
你不是这种配置啊
It wasn't like that at birth.
出生的时候也完全不是这样
You weren't someone with basic scientific literacy either.
你也不是一个具有基本科学素养的人
What I mean is,
也就是说我说了
Bilibili will always be for the top 6.5% of Chinese people.
B站永远是中国的前6.5%
That part of the young generation,
那那那部分年轻人
Most real fire-ghost teenagers and girls,
大部分真实的鬼火少年小妹之类的
They generally don't visit Bilibili.
你他们一般不会上B站
Or they might visit when they were much younger,
或者他们特别年轻的时候会上
But they won't watch it when they are in their twenties or thirties.
但是他们二三十岁的时候就不会看了
And what are you really here for on Bilibili?
而你真正通过B站你还来干嘛
You're here to gain knowledge from different social strata.
你是来获取不同阶层的知识的
This is the most critical part for you.
这个是你最关键的一部分
So, we always say that we can never completely avoid it,
所以来讲我们说我们永远无法完全的避开啊
the unfair phenomena in society.
社会当中的不公平的现象
Many of these are historical legacies,
很多东西它是一种历史的沉淀
and some are the harsh realities of today.
也有东西是现实当中的无奈
But no matter what,
但无论如何
you just need to figure out one thing. First, as a person how do you survive? Second, simply put, how do I change my surroundings? using whatever small resources I have So, have I figured out this question?
你只要想明白一件事 一你作为一个人 你如何生存下去 二最简单来讲就是我如何去改变我周围的环境 用我尽我的绵薄之地啊 所以我想明白了这个问题了吗
When I was young
我在年轻的时候
I also pursued fairness and justice passionately
我也非常追求公平与正义
But I found that those ideals
但我发现我的那些东西
those outbursts
那些宣泄啊
All those complaints and grievances
那些满满腹的那种牢骚啊
In the end
其实到最后来讲的话
we all face one issue
都要面临一个问题
our own survival
就是我自身的生存
the question of existence and extinction
那个存亡绝学的问题
If I can't even solve my own survival
如果自身的生存我都解决不了的话
what's the point of practicing swordsmanship every day
我天天舞刀弄枪的啊
and making a big fuss
吆五喝六的
What's the use of it all?
那有什么用呢
So, talking about it,
所以来讲的话
I've noticed that the more you hate someone,
我发现呵你越是讨厌谁
the more you need to work for them.
你就越是需要给谁工作啊
Do you think I would work for those rich second generations?
你想我就给那些富二代工作嘛
Right?
对不对
In exchange, I gained my initial capital.
换取了我的原始资金
This initial capital made my survival much easier.
我的原始资金又导致了我的生存变得不再难了
So that's how it is.
所以就是这样
Many things go against common sense.
所以很多东西都是反常识的
You want to fight for the interests of the hardworking common people
你想为普通的劳苦大众去争取利益
That's the right thing to do
这个东西是对的
It shows that you have a kind heart
这个东西证明你有一颗善心
You are a normal person
你是一个正常的人
You are someone with compassion
你是一个有同情心的人
A person with empathy Someone who has a merciful heart But when you serve these people You also need to understand them What you do for them they don't have the means to pay you back
你是一个同理心 有慈悲心的人 但是你为了这些人服务的时候 你也要明白这些人的这些 你为他做的事情 他们没有能力回报你
and that's the most frustrating part
这就是最要命的事情
you'll find that those who seem to take advantage
你会发现那些看起来巧取豪夺的
like the wealthy
那些富豪之类的
they will find ways to return the favor
他们会用他们的方式回报你
that's the counterintuitive part
这个就是比较反常识的地方
when you help the poor
就是你帮助穷人
the poor can actually solve fewer problems for you
穷人能够为你解决的问题其实并不多
Because his own survival energy is relatively low
因为他自己的生存能量比较小
But when you help the rich solve problems
但是你帮富人解决问题
You act as the rich's lackey to address some of their
你当富人的狗腿子给他们去解决一些
actual issues
他们实际的问题的
The rewards you receive will always be substantial
你能得到的回报呢永远是多的
So let me tell you
所以我跟你说
The right path in life
一个人生的正确道路
Is to work for the rich
就是你要为富人工作
To solve their pressing concerns
你要为他们解决一些燃眉之急
You need to be their lackey
你要当他们的狗腿子
and then use the money they earn to help the poor
然后用他们从那赚到的钱再去帮助穷人
Of course, by the time you're 30
当然来讲你有可能到30岁的时候
or 40
到40岁的时候
or even 50
到50岁的时候
you might not think that way anymore
你就不这么想了
by then, you might have your own kids
那时候你可能有了自己的孩子
or you might have established your own business
那时候有可能有了自己的事业
or you might have become part of a certain group
那时候你有可能成为了某一群体的一份子
You might not think that way. So the world is changing. So when you're young, What's known as a pure heart, You have some roots of kindness at this time. You must protect them well. Keep them hidden. Don't easily exploit them.
你有可能就不会这么想了 所以这个世界是会变的 所以你在你年轻的时候 所谓的赤子之心 你这时候有一些善良的根 你一定要把它保护好 把它隐藏起来 不要轻易的套路它
So in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
When we talk about it, these things are not easy.
我们说的时候就是这些东西不容易
So you'll find that Brother Rong is also a hypocritical person.
所以你会发现荣哥也是一个虚伪的人啊
Although I might say that I sympathize with the underprivileged.
我虽然嘴上会说我很同情弱势群体
I would never hand over the trash in my hands to them.
但是同样的我也绝不会把手中的垃圾交给他们
That's just it.
就是这样
I'm afraid they might turn around and bite me.
因为我怕他们反过来咬我一口
It's that simple.
就这么简单
This is the survival dilemma of the intelligentsia.
这就是知识分子的生存困境
He has a compassionate personality.
他具有悲天悯人的个性啊
It's hard to say,
它具有怎么说呢
a universal value,
一种普世价值
a value of standing up for the hardworking masses,
一种为天下劳苦大众啊出头的价值
but once his social status,
但是一旦当他自己的阶级地位
rises to the wealthy class,
提升到富人的阶级
or the elite class,
或者提升到精英阶层的时候
his considerations change,
他这时候考虑的东西就不一样了
firstly, to ensure his class status doesn’t slip,
首先是要确定自己的阶级不会滑落
to secure his living condition,
确定自己的生存状态
and that his family members remain in this system,
自己的家庭成员仍然在这个荒东西当中
the issues you consider,
当你去考虑的问题
like what Brother Rong is considering now,
就像荣哥现在考虑的问题
is whether I should start a Pangdonglai supermarket, not whether I should return to the U.S. or Canada, right? This is my top priority, as I always say,
我是去考虑我应该成立一个胖东来超市吗 我不是我首先考虑的应该怎么样回美国 加拿大 哼哼对不对 这是我最先考虑的事情 因为我还是那句话说
making money from the rich is relatively easier,
赚富人的钱相对要容易一些
especially when it comes to making money from wealthy Chinese,
赚富有的中国人的钱来讲
it’s much easier compared to making money from ordinary people,
其实最相对来讲比挣普通人的钱要容易得多啊
so this is a simpler path in life,
所以这也是人生的一个比较简单之道
which means you are still serving the rich,
也就是说你仍然是在为富人服务啊
the world has no such responsibility,
这个世界没有任何责任
no simple and straightforward truth,
没有任何简简单单的道理
that can be universally applied,
可以说放之四海皆准的
so that’s how reality works,
所以现实当中就是这样啊
I’ve tasted the sweetness from this way of working,
我也从当中的这种劳动方式中呢尝到了甜头
so I will continue with this model,
所以我会继续这种模式下去
for me,
所以对于我来讲
I just want to live a good life,
我只想把这一生过好了啊
I just want to live a simpler life,
对我想只想去一些比较简单的生存
in a place that’s not so competitive,
比较不是那么卷的地方去生活
but still, the original question remains,
但同样来讲还是那个原始的问题
are we beekeepers or honey?
我们到底是养蜂人还是蜂蜜呢
or bees?
还是蜜蜂呢
you must understand this principle,
你一定要明白这个道理
of course,
当然来讲的话
I think the best thing is to be a beekeeper,
我觉得最好的东西呢就是做养蜂人
being a beekeeper always has better luck,
做养蜂人永远的一个运会
luck, than a bee’s luck, this is the reality of the capital game.
运气啊 要好过蜜蜂的运气啊 这也就是这个资本游戏的真实的情况所在